<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Denus petition to the Lord General Cromwell with his Protestation and engagement : also, his description of the house of God and original priesthood : whereunto is annexed The ministerial duty and The personal reign of the saints.</title>
            <author>Denus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1068A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09362288</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09362288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1307:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Denus petition to the Lord General Cromwell with his Protestation and engagement : also, his description of the house of God and original priesthood : whereunto is annexed The ministerial duty and The personal reign of the saints.</title>
                  <author>Denus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Colophon: London : Printed for Henry Hasilwood, 1651.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DENUS PETITION To the Lord General CROMWELL.</p>
            <p>WITH, His Proteſtation, and Engagement.</p>
            <p>ALSO, His Deſcription of the Houſe of God, and Original Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſterial Duty; And the Perſonal Reign of the Saints.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. H.</hi> MDCLI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:42837:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42837:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, OLIVER Lord CROMWEL. <hi>The humble Petition and ſupplication of me poor</hi> Denus.</head>
            <p>THeſe are to certifie your Highneſſe, hoping that with all moderation you will be pleaſed to condeſcend ſo low as to behold and peruſe my meſſage from God. It is not an Army or an arm of fleſh, but the power of God that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeth you; he is the Lord to whom all the powers of the earth ſhall ſtoop, and throw down their Crowns and all their outward honour. For at his appearing man ought not to aſcribe or Image out to himſelf the name <hi>(Lord)</hi> or in any graven ſubſtance; for now he reigneth King upon his Throne ſince the 13 &amp; 14 dayes of April laſt paſt, iſſuing 1650. being <hi>Eaſter</hi> day, and the day before, called the Jewes Saturday: and I <hi>Denus</hi> appeared to make known the day of the Lord and his year excepted: and this viſible Power did firſt Oriently appear in the City of <hi>London,</hi> by four proclamations being placed in the four Corners of the old <hi>Exchange,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a great change of States, of Lawes, of Governments, of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, of Merchandize, of Prieſts, of Opinions, and a change of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Condition. Sir, it is in your power to do good, Oh that you would ſee the end of your Work, and higheſt enjoyments; there be many refreſhments which be Enſigns of Gods Love, but none ſo precious as this, which is to live in God. I hope you ſtrive not for honour, nor yet for any outward preheminence, but onely for the glory of Chriſt, and primitive purity; if you have any by-end below him, it will not proſper: for that which is of God will ſtand, when all other things will decay. I hope your End is to reduce and to bring all things unto their former Original, to heal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the breaches, then you ſhall be called the Reſtorer of places to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42837:3"/>dwell in. Now this your preheminence is to the Work of God, and conſider it, I pray you; It is a curſed thing to do Gods work ſlightly; and an honourable thing to appear for Chriſt in caſe of greateſt danger. You have been proſperous, God was and is your defence. Lord ſay ride on and proſper. Your Army is his Battel Ax, and ſhould deſtroy humane powers, fully to maintain Chriſt's power: for other powers I know none that ſhall ſtand before him. Now that you would pleaſe to ſtand up for a free Nation, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promiſes made to our <hi>Commonalty,</hi> and not onely for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but for reſtoration, the one without the other is not available; therefore that it may pleaſe you to ſee the great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among us which be ſo inhumane and ſavage, that ſo violently they ſpoil and eat out the heart of our Canaan, and deſtroy a good Land. Oh that you would ſtand up to help the poor of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and where you find great Parſonages where the Diviners have and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>njoy too much, that ſome of it might be diſtributed in the ſame places. Oh that you would pleaſe to impropriate to them, I mean the helpleſſe and diſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed of our Nation, and that you would take in conſideration to do good with all impropriations, and deal with the Butcher Townes according to their deſerts: but queſtionleſſe they will ſay, we or our fathers have bought them with our money. It may be ſo, but whence did Tythes ariſe? Though <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt paid Tythes of all to <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his whole Subſtance was liable to Chriſt, having neither end nor beginning. Or can you ſhew the lawful buying of tythes? if the Miniſter poſſeſſeth them not, why ſhould great men hold them? for ought we know they are proper to the poor of ſuch places, and for Gods houſe. The holy Scriptures adde to this purpoſe by an alluſion to the Church, as he ſaith elſewhere; <hi>That ye do to any of thoſe little ones, ye do it to me:</hi> and theſe things keeping away, are but Robbing his houſe of common Rites. I pray you what tythes were given in the Apoſtles time? thoſe Miniſters could not be ſo proud, nor their wives neither: Or what impropriations or Church-Robbers without <hi>Judas</hi> was one? Or which were the beſt of them that ſold the Church Rites, or them that bought them? They may both run in one chanel, for they neither bought nor ſold their own; nor can they lawfully hold the tythes from the poor and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42837:3"/>houſe of God; for God may well ſay, <hi>Why do ye rob me in Tythes and offerings? You ſhall not keep my Feast of Tabernacles, nor come into my reſt, or inward Courts.</hi> There be many other diſhonourable over-ruling evills in our Nation, which you may pleaſe to vindicate to the Parliament, that there might be a redreſſement, by a reſtoring pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which may be very comfortable to our ſtate; and in ſo doing, God may be fully ſeen in your work, and will anſwer your deſires. It were good if the poor of every Pariſh could have what helps might be within their own Liberties, as Commons and ancient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments. Our Parliament might ſee this, God ſeeth it and ſaith their Captivity ſhall return, it is onely meant the captivity of the poor; for the rich be not in that Snare, but in a more deep and dangerou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condition. The poor cry, and are ſent empty away, but the Rich ſhall have many places, and this will be a fire-brand in ſome of their conſciences, when they ſhall remember and ſo be ſhut out from the enjoyment of God, for he can as well give com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the poor in their affliction, and give others hell in their great poſſeſſions; for at the end every foundation ſhall ſtand upon their own bottome: I cannot but declare the things of God. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your poor petitioner intreateth you to take into your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the abuſess of all Common Deſtroyers of our good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth or well being. It hath formerly been, when a dear year hath come, the poor have paid for it; but now we cannot find it ſo, others will pay for it before them; we have ſo many that do ingroſſe priviledges, and are loth that the ruſt of their money ſhould not be a witneſſe againſt them; therefore they buy whole Lordſhips, though the earth be the Lords and not theirs, yet they can make it their own from men, untill the Lord blow upon it: thus they build Babylon to their hearts deſire, which muſt ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall. There be many other great offenders which keep up and impriſon plenty, hoarding up many hundred Quarters of Corne, buying it contrary to the Will of the Lord, and ſo eat out the heart and name of plenty, to ingroſſe as they do. We have ſome Badger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Woolves that will come between the ficle and the ſythe, ſaying, I will give thus much, or ſuch a Rate for Corn all the year about: and thus they Witch up the prices of corn. Theſe are abominable branches, and theeves to the Common wealths good. All theſe and ſuch as theſe be, would be branded with the letter G. ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42837:4"/>God hath plagued thee. Now this publick theft is far worſe then poor poverteous theft; for poor poverty judgeth the law, and juſtifieth it ſelf. When the world and all outward means fail, yet God will be ſeen in equity, and will juſtifie the poor mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in a way of conſideration. <hi>Sir,</hi> you and all the Parliament ſhould be the breaſts of our Conſolation, yet we know not how you will order our Common wealths affaires, which as yet we lye under your veyl and liable to your Diſpoſing, not yet enjoying a free National ſtability, according to Gods Inſtitution or Creation, but to live in hope and above hope, looking beyond all outward externals, which is nothing in his ſight. Now the Over-ruling power and providence of God guide you in thoſe great affaires you take in hand. Yet further to let you underſtand, we lie yet in Darkneſſe under a ſad Diſpenſation betwixt a King, and an unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led State full of murmurings, diſtractions, and declinings from true godlineſſe, working our own ends by perſonal greatneſſe, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſweet enjoyment we might have in God, if we did not ſo highly prize this fading world; but to ſee nothing honourable, below Chriſt, but all mens honours ſhall quake as an Aſpen leafe, and none ſhall hold but that of godlineſſe. Who is afflicted and I not, or who ſhall declare, but I from the Lord? I fear not to ſpeak the truth in the Lords Deſign. I can have no reſt night nor day untill I ſee his work accompliſhed; but there is much covetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and oppreſſion in our Nation, that as yet we muſt not ſay our God is a reconciled God; but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill, untill he hath bent <hi>Juda</hi> and gathered in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and reſtored <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and untill then the ſword ſhall drink bloud and ſhall not ceaſe: is it riches, honour, or greatneſſe ye ſtrive for? O take the beſt Seaſon and goldeneſt Opportunity; it is not an outward en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment will make you inwardly happy, but in that you tread down all principalities and powers for Chriſt Jeſus his Crown and Dignities; and that is the higheſt appearance and fulleſt power, and God will crown the works of all his Saints that ſtand up for his Kingly Power; and I beſeech you to lay down your honour at Chriſts feet, and then you ſhall be exalted: <hi>for things in heaven, and things on earth, and things under the earth, muſt bowe at the Name of Jeſus and at his appearance;</hi> for God will bring down the high ſpirits of <hi>Mount Seir</hi> and <hi>Capernaum,</hi> and he haughtineſſe of the proud earth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42837:4"/>ſhall come down, and the humble ſhall be exalted: for the Lord will raiſe the honour of his Son, that hath been long crucified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worlds tyranny, ſo that at his appearing both Lord and King ſhall refuſe their titles of honour. I ſpeak not this to your diſgrace, but to <hi>ſpeak the things I have heard and ſeen,</hi> Act. 4.20. and I dare not but appear for Chriſt in the face of fire and faggot, or greateſt damp or danger. I am a poor man, I am ſure I need not look for honour; neither do I acknowledge any thing honourable below Chriſt; therefore in truth, Lord, your honour muſt fall at his appearing. O would to God you would make known that which cannot be hid: for now it is high time to awake, that Sion ſhould put on ſtrength; for now it is come to the birth, and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your help to bring forth. O that you would pleaſe to ſtand up to maintain true Judgment, that Juſtice may run down our ſtreets; ſo you ſhall proſper in bleſſings, even as a garden refreſhed with ſweet drops from above; verily ye ſhall be as the morning Star in brightneſſe to paſſe: the Lord ſhall bleſſe your going out and your comig in, he ſhall be your conſolation and great peace, and much happineſſe ſhall attend your gates. The Work in hand is, to raiſe the Tabernacle of David that is fallen, which is a reſtoring of many generations. The duty we are Obliged is to build Gods houſe, and to deſtroy all other foundations, and to come into one fold, which is Chriſts ſheepfold, called the new Model or Jeweſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Fabrick. We are all bound to build up the partition wall, that hath been trod down ſo long, even the holy City which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Lord telleth us ſhall be trod down untill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles come in, <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.14. &amp; the 3. &amp; 5. he is your King. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>I will betroth thee unto me in loving kindneſſe and in mercy.</hi> Make the Lord your King, he is your King, which if you do, the high Lord will bleſſe you in your good name, in your perſon, and in your eſtate, and will raiſe good out of your generations, that you may be called the Repairer of the breach, and reſtorer of paths to dwell in. He is your King. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. <hi>thou haſt a perfect crown of gold upon his head. Pſalm</hi> 22. <hi>For the Kingdome is the Lords, and he is the Governour among the Nations.</hi> Pſalm 2. <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill Sion.</hi> His Kingly power was ſeen in <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Pſalm 150.21, 22. <hi>He made him Ruler over all his ſubſtance, to bind his Princes at his pleaſure, and to teach his Senatours wiſdome: he ſet Moiſes his ſervant, and Aaron
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42837:5"/>whom he had choſen, and his wonders was ſeen in the Land of Ham.</hi> And the Prophet John ſaith, <hi>he that overcometh ſhall rule the Nations with a rod of iron.</hi> Surely our God ſhall do this and greater things. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other great example under the type of <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> Joſ. 3. <hi>If thou wilt walk in my ways, and if thou wilt keep my charge, then ſhalt thou judge my Houſe, and keep my Court, and I will give thee places with them that ſtand by.</hi> In this we ſee that God is ever ready to crown a good work; alſo, they that be faithful to God, he will be faithful to them.</p>
            <p>Further, that your Excellency would be pleaſed to let the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners go free, that their cry may not come up to the Lord; by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſome of them have died in priſon by ſalvage cruelty: There is no Nation under heaven but do allow their priſoners ſomething, if it be but bread and water, but in truth ſome have not had that allowance, which is not Chriſtian-like, being kept there having no relief nor ſupport. Is God ſeen in it, or ſhall he not contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe for theſe things? Open your priſon gates for pity, and let offenders be branded as bond-ſervants with a letter, to be known to whom they have offended, and ſo to reſtore as they be able; and and not to keep them in hell upon earth: Alſo it is manifeſted, that ſome poor godly Chriſtians have loſt their lives, denying their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, not having juſtice, which were their arrears, deſiring it for their wives and could not have it, and ſo denied to go forth, which cauſed the loſs of life: And it hath been a woful ſpectacle in the worlds eye, when it hath been apparently known that ſome devouring <hi>Nimrods</hi> have bought out many poor ſouldiers pay, ſome for 4<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, 5<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, or 6<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, in the ſcore, and all for want of juſtice; Their cries will come up to the God of heaven. I beſeech your Excellence promote true juſtice, for Gods cauſe, and fear no human fleſh, and the Lord will be your arm of defence. <hi>Oh Army of the Lord,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, 1.26. <hi>I will restore thy judgments as at the firſt, and thou ſhalt be called the City of Righteouſneſs, when Sion ſhall be redeemed with juſtice, and when you ſhall redeem the oppreſſed, judge the fatherleſs, and plead for the widow, then the Lord will delight in your works of piety.</hi> Now that it may pleaſe you to take into your conſideration, and to move our Parliament upon the Lords deſigne; that both they and you may be called bleſſed in the act of Reſtoring; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.14. the Lord declareth, ſaying; <hi>Ye ſhall one inherit as well as another:</hi> Meaning the Earth, or the Land which is the Lords. <hi>Verſe</hi> the 22 he ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall divide the Land by lot, for an inheritance.</hi> And laſtly he ſaith,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42837:5"/>
               <hi>What Tribe ſoever the ſtranger ſojourneth in, there ye ſhall give him his inheritance:</hi> Now the clamation of our poor <hi>Iſrael</hi> is for want of Commons to plant and build upon; and this being alienated and eſtranged from them by curſed <hi>Ahabs,</hi> which now do enjoy <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, and ſpoil our good Commons. The Lord hath ſent me to move you upon this object, that they which have poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhould not take away the Commons from the poor Common wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but that they which have no inheritance ſhould have their Lots in the Commons, as it is their right by Creation, from God, the Prophets, Eſay, Jeremy, and Ezekiel, ſhall be til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and become as the garden of <hi>Eden.</hi> Joel 3.2. <hi>I will plead with them for my people Iſrael, and for my heritage, which they have caſt lots for my land, and parted it among the Nation.</hi> Now if your Excellency pleaſe to help the Lord againſt the mighty, then he ſaith, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>I will reſtore to you the years that the Locuſts have eaten, the Cankerworm, the Caterpiller, and the Palinerworm which I ſent amongſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, That you would pleaſe to fall and kneel at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord, when he ſhall ſet up his Ordination or Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Power, then all your ſubordinate powers muſt fall: then he that is leaſt in the world, ſhall be greateſt in his Kingdome; and he that overcometh ſhall rule the Nations. Let the high praiſes of God be in your mouth, and a two edged ſword in your hand, to deſtroy ſin, for a ſpiritual and temporal Juſtice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So I reſt, your poor petitioner to command,</hi> Denus <hi>to the reſtored Church in the Iſle of</hi> Pathmos.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42837:6"/>
            <head>A Proteſtation and Engagement.</head>
            <p>I Am ingaged for the Cauſe, and ſhall lay down my life and deareſt blood, and will do it in caſe of conſcience, for the defence of the everlasting Goſpel; though humane Lawes do fail, and mens ordinances come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet how unchangeable is the Law of God in his ordination? Chriſt at his first appearance destroyed every mans law and ordinances, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon wounded the Beaſt, ſaying, <hi>All power is given me in heaven and in earth, Go teach all Nations;</hi> as if be ſhould ſay, every law, sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and ordinance of man is at an end, yet many ſtrive for earthly and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane power, and cauſe the ſword to rule by a law, which is not the Law of God, to kill and keep alive, although for common treſpaſſes, making their own wills a law, contrary to the law of Sion; and we hold up the ſword by a law, and a law by the ſword, which is not good; our Lord ſaith, <hi>he that killeth with the ſword, ſhall dye with the ſword.</hi> He in <hi>Geneſis, Whoſoever killeth Cain, his blood ſhall be required ſeven fold:</hi> and Revel. <hi>11. Whoſoever killeth them ſhall be ſo killed:</hi> tt is better for a man to dye an Anatomy, then to be a man-ſlayer, to take away life and free Creation from any of the Creatures of God, and to lord over them by cruelty. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>offences will be, but woe be to them by whom they do come, it were better a milſtone were hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about his neck and caſt into the Sea, then to offend</hi> in bloud, robbery, or any ſuch thing by legal cruelty, pretending a law above the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and Records of Chriſt to his Diſciples, which law to maintain, is not ſo ancient as that order of Melchizedeck made to Abraham by a promiſe, though <hi>the law was given by Moſes, yet faith and truth came by Chriſt.</hi> So that under the name of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> or under the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he the Lord hath alwayes put an end to mans ordinances according to his Divine Ordination; and I know no law of man that can stand before the Law of God in Sion: there is but one Law, and one Law-giver, which gift to us is the free Goſpel, as <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>So ſpeak, and ſo walk,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42837:6"/>that ye may be judged by the Law of liberty, which is the Word of God;</hi> for an outward record called by <hi>David</hi> his <hi>Statutes Divine,</hi> meaning the Old and New Teſtament, by way of cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that every godly Magiſtrate ſhould lay the Bible book before him, to convince every ſinne and errour of the offender, and not to uſe any other book of mixture compounded together, leſt they adde or diminiſh from Gods Word or Commandment; for then, and at that time, the Bible ſhall be the chief Statute to maintain Freedome and Juſtice: it is not your statutes of <hi>Wincheſter, London,</hi> or <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſo Evangelical or ancient that can ſtand when the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt appeareth, and ſhall ſhine out of the Eaſt unto the Weſt, and from the North to the South, ſo that all the Nations ſhall ſee his glorious appearing; which is his teſtimony of Light to me a ſufferer for the Goſpel of Chriſt: and I know not whether by impriſonment or loſſe of life, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is but freedomes purgatory, and it ſhall at the laſt conquer hell, and Freedome ſhall have victory by his ſtatutes Divine: it is for the Law of God that I dye daily, and am much killed in my dear Deſires. I ſtand up for the liberty of the Goſpel, and Freedome of the Creation, and to plead for the Kingdome of Chriſt and the inheritance of the people, which I hope you will not hinder me of: Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Matth. 10. Fear them not;</hi> for there is nothing hid that ſhall not be known, and I cannot but declare the things I have ſeen. I am not onely ready to ſuffer your impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, but to ſuffer death or any torture for the Cauſe, I mean for the Law and Liberties of the Goſpel of the Lord. I am a faithful witneſſe of God, I fear not your Famine, Distreſſe or Death; I am the perſon to raiſe <hi>Johns</hi> teſtimony, he was <hi>Juda,</hi> and I am <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Denus</hi> the feet of the two Witneſſes.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Septemb. 29 1651.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42837:7"/>
            <head>The Law of Sion.</head>
            <p>HEre is an Alligory of two Lawes; the firſt is the ſingular and pure Law of God; the other is the unjuſt lawes of Man. This pure Law of God ſhall put an end to all the lawes of man upon the ſeventh Vial; this Law of God gendereth to life and ſalvation, but the lawes of man do gender to cruelty and corruption; which lawes of man muſt fall before <hi>Sion,</hi> which are not lawes according to his Word and true equity; all ſuch lawes are but mens ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and ſhall not ſtand before the <hi>Law of God:</hi> for there is but one Law, and one Law-giver, which is God that hath given us his Word for a Law to be a reſtoring right to all: and for want of this true execution of Gods word, it maketh the curſe remain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creature to this day, and becauſe of forbidden fruit, which is contrary to his Inſtitution maketh it ſo; but Gods word ſhould be ſet in its place, to judge or condemn, to ſave or juſtifie, and not mens traditions which are vain: Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Man liveth not onely by bread, but by every word that cometh out of Gods mouth;</hi> which is from his ancient Decree to keep all things by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which is a hidden law, and ſpiritual and agreeable to the letter of his Word: and I know no other law that man can erect, but to judge all things by the law of Gods Word, and to throw down mens ordinances which be not agreeable to it: for ſuch lawes proceed not out of Sion, neither can our Judges be Judges in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> except they make Gods word the rule of juſtice to try cauſes by: And going contrary to this Rule, it maketh many fleſhly Judges and weak Jury-men (O ſimple ignorance and baſe folly) to go from the Judge of Heaven and Earth, to ſerve under theſe Judges which deſtroy his Word and Law of juſtice: for there is no offence committed before God or againſt man, but may be judged by his word of Truth and pure Goſpel under the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Chriſt and his Church, which may be called <hi>Jure Divino,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42837:7"/>that is, under twelve holy perſons, or ſo many Senatours of Gods houſe, that your law may wholly proceed out of Sion, that Divine Juſtice may cenſure all judicature power, and ſo to tread them under feet with the ſcarlet whore which have taken away many mens lives contrary to Gods word and holy Scripture: it hath been a poor buſineſſe carried on ſo long, that wicked Judges ſhould ſit to give ſentence, and ſome wicked fore-men among the reſt ſhould give up their verdict contrary to the <hi>Law of Sion,</hi> having judged for reward, and ſome for want of ſeeing the pure Will of God, and declaration of his word: his word ought to judge and govern, and ſhall throw down all oppreſſing, that his people may have reſt from all their enemies: theſe Judges have been in ſuch eſteem before men, and yet ignorant of Divine juſtice which he hath ſet before them in his Word. I deſire you all to know both Judge and Juſtice; if you adde or diminiſh from Gods VVord, it will prove unjuſtice, and therein ye fall ſeverity, and hinder the free paſſage of the Goſpel, changing it into your own ordinances, uſing the Goſpel to your own turns, which is a curſed thing to do; your lawes are of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which ſhall periſh in <hi>Armagiddon,</hi> and fall by deſtruction: ye <hi>Judges, Lawyers, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> your ordinances ſhall burn with <hi>Babylon,</hi> and your ſeven ſtreams of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er are ſtruck by the ſeventh Vial of Gods wrath, &amp; his Law muſt go out of Sion, which ſhall caſt out all your laws, that juſtice may run down our ſtreets. What makes ſo much bauling in our Churches? To anſwer, it is becauſe they go on hood-winked, compounding the lawes of men amongſt the ordinances of God, which be far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant the one from the other: and for want of the true executing of this word of God, all your Churches are in a combuſtion, as Bees up in armes one againſt another for the truth; and untill we make Gods word the Rule and Law of our civil affaires, to bring our ſelves under the Captivity of Chriſt, and untill then, the curſe ſhall remain, I properly mean the curſed lawes of man, which have bought and ſold the lives of ſome men contrary to the Word of God, and <hi>Law of Sion:</hi> this curſe, or curſed ordinance of man, God will ſuddenly burn up and aboliſh by the brightneſſe of his appearing: and <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are they that keep his teſtimonies; thy word have I hid in my heart, that I might not ſin againſt thee: I will not forget thy word: Princes did ſit and ſpeak againſt me, but I did medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42837:8"/>in thy ſtatutes devine: Thy Law is my counſel day and night; I have more underſtanding then all my Teachers; I underſtand more then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, becauſe I keep thy Law. I have refrained my feet from every evill way, becauſe of thy word, How ſweet are thy words unto my taſte? Thy word is a light to my feet, quicken me according to thy word. mine eyes prevent the night watch. I beheld the tranſgreſſours and was grieved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they kept not thy word: Tears run down mine eyes, becauſe they keep not thy word.</hi> Now if our Lawyers would truly ſee this Law of God, they durſt not do as they do; and if our Judges would prove cauſes by this word of God, then might we call them the <hi>Judges in Iſrael;</hi> but it is not ſo, for they prove their own teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and act ſin by a law: but look into this 119. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and ye ſhall find it pithy to this purpoſe, he calleth it <hi>thy Statutes divine,</hi> which if our Magiſtrates did but ſavingly look in this glaſſe of Gods law, they might well throw away their books, which be but the ſtep-mother to this <hi>Law of Sion,</hi> called mens ordinances, which have thus traded in power over Gods word and true Goſpel, untill the year of our Lord, 1650. which was then ſhaken, though not utterly faln, yet it ſhall loſe its ſhining light of oriency, and tho Lawyers and Judges ſhall never gain credit nor comfort, until they do erect the true word of God far above the ſtatutes of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. there ye may find at large, that <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> made of the Levites, and of the Prieſts, and of the chiefeſt of the Fathers of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> for the judgment of the Lord, and for all Controverſies. And in that ye may find he did not ſet the ungodly to judge, nor bloudy men that ſhould judge according to their own wills, but ſuch as were choſen men of the Lord that ſhould make his holy word the rule of juſtice to end all differences: Now good <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> gave the Judges a charge, ſaying, <hi>Take heed what ye do, ye judge not for man, but for the Lord who is with you in the judgment: take heed and do it, for there is no iniquity with our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts:</hi> and he charged them, ſaying, <hi>Thus ſhall ye do in the fear of the Lord faithfully and with a perfect heart, and what cauſe ſoever ſhall come to you betwixt blood and blood, betwixt law and commandment, ſtatute and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let them not treſpaſſe againſt the Lord.</hi> Look upon this all ye that have contrary to this holy Law, which is the written word of God, given ſo long ſince to judge the earth: this word of Sion ſhall throw down all your witchcrafts of <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> and your night-Spels
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42837:8"/>of ſubtilty; for ye have not judged according to the holy word of God. Some may ſay, Woe to you Judges, Lawyers, and Juries, for deſtroying the declaration and truth of Gods word, changing it into your own forms, and not proving all Cauſes by Scripture, all your legal rudiments muſt fall at the appearing of Sions glory, and ſhall cauſe all your Rivers in <hi>Egypt</hi> to dry up; for his word and the Saints muſt judge the earth; and your unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble juſtice ſhall fall and come to nothing, when the word of God ſhall be every mans true teſtimony to reſtore and to redreſſe, to bring again, and to reduce, to ſettle all things to their ancient Oiginal, which have been ſo long traduced from their place.</p>
            <p>And without all queſtion, the godly of the people ſhall govern, meaning, the remnant of the Tribes out of Sion; <hi>For I will cleanſe your bloud, I am the Lord that ſhall rore from thence, and utter my voice, and the earth ſhall ſhake; but I will be the hope and heritage of</hi> Jacob: He will be jealous for his land, and have pity by his redeemed, that they may have juſtice from God out of Sion: And I cannot ſee how any other law can be warrantable, but onely this word of God; and to deny all mens mixture, which are but ordinances of men and legal. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Dare any of you having a matter againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, go to law before the unjust, and not before the Saints;</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>will you bring your ſelves within the danger of the curſed laws of the Gentiles:</hi> And in Verſ, 2. he ſaith; <hi>Know you not the ſaints ſhall judge the world, and we ſhall judge Angels, much more the things that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to this life.</hi> Joel 3.2. the Lord ſaith, <hi>He will plead with all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the heritage of his people;</hi> ſaying, <hi>behold, I will raiſe them out of the place where ye have ſold them:</hi> And elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore unto you the years the Locuſts have eaten, the Canker-worm, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpiller, and Palmer-worm, which I have ſent amongſt you:</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, I will take away all the devourers that have led you captive, which have ſeduced the ſimple, carying on cauſes in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and in an unknown tongue. This is not that law which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James</hi> declareth in his ſecond Chapter, ſaying; <hi>So walk and ſo ſpeak, as you may be judged by the law of liberty</hi> (which is Sion) <hi>to try all your actions by, and ſo to be justified by Goſpel truths, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the laws of men.</hi> And wicked men ought not to bear ſway, for God will have a community, to communicate juſtice to all, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as truth ſhall guide them to this law of liberty, and Goſpel
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42837:9"/>freedom; and not by mens ordinances, that muſt fall; <hi>For mercy ſhall rejoyce over judgement, and ſhall glory over all oppreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot finde by either law or Goſpel, that men ſhould die by any outward act of theft; but the ancient records of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt only reſtitution, and if the perſon be not able to reſtore, then be a ſervant or ſlave to the perſon whom hee hath offended: The Lord ſaith, <hi>He that killeth with the ſword, ſhall die by the ſword:</hi> ſhewing, that by murther, bloud ſhall touch bloud; it were good if legal cruelty were reſtrained, as yet it hath not, but in ſhort time provided by our God, we ſhall have truth eſtabliſhed in our bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with mercy and juſtice to remain in our ſtreets; it hath been a long time mixed with Wormwood, by rigorous and cruel laws being enacted, that any malitious man that would ſwear againſt another man, whether it were right or wrong, as many times by way of ſuppoſition, not conſidering the danger of an oath, or whether it be right or wrong, the Oath being paſſed, the Jurie preſently findeth it, the plaintiffe having no way to prove the wrong done, but his own Oath, by an inditement under the King to prove the theft, making the King his grand witneſs; which hath been an intollerable mark of the beaſt, and all ye Jury-men may be aſhamed, and cover your mouths for all the bloudy Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts you have given up, look to it, for God will call you to an accompt for all your works, in that you have ſet the King to prove mens actions, which hath been a lying teſtimony, when the King hath been far diſtant from the Bench; ye corrupt Judges and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Jury-men, it hath evidently appeared by ſome that hath been wrongfully and haſtily put to death, a miſerable ſpectacle before your eys, and this is a fin that will lye heavie upon Judge and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-men, when ye ſhall take the King for a witneſs, as if he were preſent to prove the felony; this is a high principle for a knave to work his will, to prove the felony done to the Plaintiff; but draw the Curtain there, the King hath ſomething elſe to do, then to come and prove your unjuſt act: A miſerable heatheniſh law, and Turkiſh, the Turk can but demand a mans life, and what is it elſe to do in this? We ſee plainly the King may be enriched by ſuch a law, as for bringing in either to himſelf or ſome other Lord of a Mannor, felons goods, which freedom they have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed from him that is gone: And this law cannot be ſatisfied
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42837:9"/>with mans life, but wife and children muſt be utterly undone, and all taken from them by the lord of felons goods. O down with this Babylon, I wonder the world doth not violently pull her down, for they cannot be contented to take the things that were ſtoln, which is all they can have, but they will have all, then all ſhall be mine; ſo that the thing is, although he never ſtole before, and the fact be of ſmall value, yet he muſt loſe his ſweet life, and die as a dog; which is a baſe, inhumane, and ſalvage cruelty, Turkiſh and not Chriſtian-like, the juſt God and Lord Jehovah, will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confound ſuch doings. Some have been by relation, prepared for the ladder, and yet by accident the right theef hath been taken, and for the ſame fact hath ſuffered death; a heavie thing it is unto that Jurie, that ſhall cenſure a man to death by an indictment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own pretence, by an indictment in the Kings name; yet we do not juſtifie theft, but that it ſhould be lawfully proved as all other treſpaſſes be; under two witneſſes every truth ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: for one witneſſe which is the plaintiffe, may ſpeak out of envy, being his own cauſe he can be no witneſſe for himſelf; which ſheweth your lawes are unjuſt, and ſhall not ſtand, and your Judges and Lawyers may reſtore: there be three ſorts of theft; one is an incorrigible wicked theef, that will do it come life come death, many times out of envy to his brother or his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, this is a thief with a witneſſe: the ſecond, is a covetous theef which ſtealeth to enrich himſelf, theſe are both of an high nature. The third, is a thief of neceſſity, being miſerable poor and wanting; it is a ſaying amongſt us, that hunger breaks the ſtone walls: we ſee poverty cauſeth extremity, and extremity cauſeth neceſſity, and neceſſity hath no law, in caſe of conſcience: yet we cannot juſtifie the ſin of theft, and putting all into Gods hand is to ſay, <hi>The Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof.</hi> What art thou O man, to controverce with God! are thy goods thine own, or the Lords? they were his before they were thine, and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anſt not deny it; for all bleſſings proceed from God, and they are and were from him before they were thine; and if thou beeſt not a godly perſon, thou enjoyeſt that which is not thine own, and then thou art but a uſurper, and worſe in Gods account then the poor theef that ſtole for need: then let as put this in as a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat, and let us conſider it is enough to ſuffer need and want, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42837:10"/>not to ſuffer death too. There be many other things which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power and State, which to relate I cannot have time now; winding up with our Saviour and his diſciples, in caſe of neceſſity they plucked the eares of Corn, and being reproved by the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Remember David when he an hungred how he was took of the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w-bread and did eat.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Houſe of God, and Original Prieſthood.</head>
            <p>THe reaſon of my writing, is for an eſtabliſhment of Gods Houſe upon the old foundation, by a pattern from our Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and by an offering to Chriſt ſo long before his appearing in the fleſh. This Original act was for Gods houſe dues, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt bring the firſt fruits of all thy land into the houſe of the Lord thy God.</hi> Which had an alluſion to the tythes or tenths of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which was a gift to the Altar of God, for the poor in his houſe. And I cannot find but ſuch Miniſters as take away Church Rights be guilty of the ſin of Sacriledge, in robbing Gods Houſe. Bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> in the 14 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> paid tythe of all to the Lord under the name of <hi>Melchizedeck:</hi> but now our Miniſters have eat up that ordinance, and taken thoſe benefits to themſelves, blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people; and to that the Lord complaineth, <hi>Malachi</hi> the 3. ſaying, <hi>Ye have robbed me, in tythes and offerings, bring the Tythes into my ſtorehouſe.</hi> In the Apoſtles time they did not onely keep up Gods houſe, but they ſold their poſſeſſions and brought it to all the Apoſtles feet: yet now if Gods houſe were reſtored, it might be good to the Common wealth of Iſrael. The Lord ſaith, <hi>Hagg.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Ye go to your ſeiled houſes, but my houſe lyeth deſolate:</hi> and ye Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters know this, if ye bring not Tythes into Gods houſe: as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did, ſo muſt ye do, if ye do not, then God ſhall deſtroy your Temples built with ſtone. Now theſe priviledges of Gods houſe are very ancient, though for gotten, yet in the more later times of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42837:10"/>the Goſpel, the people did miniſter to the Lord of their ſubſtance, as you may find in <hi>Luke</hi> 8. by <hi>Joanna</hi> and <hi>Suſanna,</hi> and all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did miniſter unto him out of their treaſury; which ſheweth God had a houſe, whatever our Miniſters have done with it; and truly if women could do their duty to Gods houſe, it is a ſhame for men and Miniſters to <hi>Omit</hi> their ſervice to his houſe; <hi>cuſtome to whom cuſtome belongeth: Let us pay our vowes to the Lords houſe in all the peoples ſight; for now he will ſit to purifie the ſons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and will purge</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from her blood, and will come near you in Judgment,</hi> Malachi 3.9. And my brethren take heed, God is angry with you, in that you have deſtroyed the offering of his Temple. I do not mean an offering of Bullocks and Goats, nor any ſuch thing moral or Moſaical, but to do all to the ancient Order of <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi> which is Chriſt the Mediatour of a new Covenant by his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Prieſthood, which was and is a more higher Prieſthood then yours. <hi>Abraham</hi> payed Tythes of all to Chriſt long before any Law was, and it is an Order upon record to Gods houſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, and it ſhall deſtroy all carnal Covenants or mens ordinances which endure but from man to man; but this of our Saviour is and ſhall be for an endleſſe life; ye ſhall keep the charge of the Sunctuary and of the Altar, that there be no wrath any more upon the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now ye Miniſters, I am to ſummon you to perform your great Offering which you cannot deny. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.28. <hi>Ye ſhall offer up unto the Lord your Heave-offering of Tythes which ye receive of the people.</hi> Now as <hi>Aaron</hi> offered up toe <hi>Levites,</hi> ſo muſt ye to Gods Houſe, to ſettle them in their ancient place, and ſo bring again the Captivity of that Ordinance; ſo that all <hi>Prieſts, Levites,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> muſt all conſecrate the gifts of Tythes unto the Lord and his Houſe: And ye Miniſters for changing theſe Ordinances, ye be included under the ſeventh Vial of Gods wrath poured out upon the beaſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.17. declareth a voyce out of the Temple of God, ſaying, <hi>It is done.</hi> Now in the myſtery of the Vials pouring forth, the Decree of God was finiſhed, though all things not yet effected which time were to bring forth, and now is revealed upon the beaſt, which is the great plague of the world that we lye under, which is ſeven Ordinances or Vials of his wrath; whereof this curſe hath been poured out upon all, and not onely a curſe, but a curſe under theſe ſeven Ordinances, which Jew and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42837:11"/>Gentile hath not as yet made up theſe ſeven breaches of unity, which is a full ſtanding up for Goſpel Truths, which being thus omitted by Miniſter and people, cauſeth him to complain, ſaying, <hi>What are thoſe wounds in thine hand? then he ſaid unto me, They were thoſe wherewith I was wounded in the houſe of my friend:</hi> So that it grieved God to ſee prophaneneſſe both in prieſt and people, ſaying, <hi>I took my staffe beauty and cut it in ſunder, that I might break my Covenant made with Jacob.</hi> Now when the Lord ſhall cut aſunder the other ſtaffe bonds which is now among us, then all your priſon gates ſhall be open, and there ſhall be a ſtanding up for the eternal <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> in every Nation. <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.3. there is an howling of the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, for their glory is ſpoyled: verſe the 15. he ſaith, <hi>Take to thy ſelf the inſtruments of a fooliſh ſhepherd:</hi> Shewing ſome poor deſpiſed Meſſenger that God ſhall ſend to lay the Miniſters under wrath by the ſeventh Vial.</p>
            <p>Now a pouring forth, further he ſaith in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Woe to the idle ſhepherds that leave their flock, his arm ſhall be clean dryed up, and his right eye darkened upon the ſounding the alarm in Sion;</hi> which is the pouring out of the laſt Vial, which produceth Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice in the Earth: and by a ſtanding up for it when all the Earth ſhall be awaked to maintain the Creation of Gods inheritance or inſtitution: Theſe ſeven Vials make out one fulneſſe, that is, all the fulneſſe of Gods time, and to that end they be called <hi>Vials;</hi> ſix of them are poured out already, the ſeventh is now in power, pouring forth: which is Kingdome power and glory, for an infallible teſtimony of his bright appearing, which is called the ſeventh and laſt Vial, which ſhall violate and burn up every <hi>All</hi> under it, called ſix <hi>Alls</hi> or Vial Ordinances, that ſhall be purged by it. This is King over all the other ſix Ordinances, whereon all things muſt be proved upon the Center, called the Everlaſting Word, ſaying, <hi>All power is given me, in heaven and in earth.</hi> Thus all Powers dye, and live in him, by one Power, which is true Goſpel; for he is the Fountain of every Original, and at his appearance every Religion ſhall be purged, and all conditions changed, and ſhall darken all things at his bright appearing, and under this everlaſting Goſpel or ſeventh Vial, many ſhall be ſlain and fall under Gods hand; for it ſhall try the Conſciences of men, and it ſhall judge all the Ordinances. Who can but fear thee, O
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42837:11"/>Lord, <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. for thy Judgments are made manifeſt, and the light is diſcovered that hath layn hid ſo long, and God is taking off the vail, and covering ſpread over all fleſh, and Judgment muſt firſt begin at his own houſe, and every petty prieſthood muſt fall; for behold the conſtellations ſhall fail, the Sun and the Moon, and Miniſters may fail, but his eternal Prieſthood ſhall ſtand for ever: the Stars or Lights ſhall fall before him, which is true Goſpel; and I know no other Goſpel, but that of Chriſt and his Apoſtles which is not fully preached forth, nor actually performed: but the Lord will now make all things new, a new heaven, a new earth, a new Covenant, and a new Goſpel, and old things muſt become new; and though they have layn in darkneſſe under ſix or ſeven Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of time to make out the end of their darkneſſe, yet now the pure Light will ſpring that ſhall aboliſh all under it: and his pure Ordinance is now in pouring forth, which is his Sabbaths Vial, it ſhall judge all her abominations, and all her oppreſſions, and ſhall make out all the Goſpel Promiſes and priviledges, by every out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward performance. For it is not your peeced out cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or any meritorious work of your hand that God looketh for. Thou muſt bring thine offering into Gods houſe; for thoſe that be deſtitute of comfort muſt have and receive of the gift from the Altar, and not from any mans perſonal gift: neither can it be ſo proper as from God and his Church, as given from a Fountain, and from his houſe muſt relief come, which is from the Altar of God, ſo the left hand ſhall not know what the right hand doth; for it ſhall ariſe from the Tythes or Tenth part of the ſubſtance under Gods hand; as if we ſhould all ſay, we give thee this from the overplus, which is a feeding together in one propriety of an enjoyment under God; ſo that every mans Tythes being conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to Gods houſe, ſhould make up every breach, that Charity may have its perfect work to fulfill the Law of Liberty, which is a Goſpel freedome from the firſt <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> which may be called an endleſſe freedome for the creatures of God to enjoy, and ſo to make his houſe a Common Treaſury to the peodle, and not to command Tythes as Dues to the Miniſter; neither can ye lawfully demand it, either by Law or Goſpel, if ye can, then diſprove this which is written. What if the Miniſter ſhall receive Tythes, yet he is to bring it into Gods houſe for an offering, and not to enrich
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42837:12"/>himſelf, but to be contented with the meaneſt condition, to be humble to God, and lowly to man, and in ſo doing he ſhall not defile the offering of Gods Temple, nor make his Ordinance a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane thing which our Miniſters have formerly done. Prieſt I am your Inheritance, ſaith the Lord; and no other inheritance can you have of God: for the overplus of his houſe is for you to eat and to drink with the ſtranger, the fathenleſſe, and the widow. What if thy Tythes be charged into Gods Houſe, it is the ſeventh part of thy gift that God looks for, which ſhall make up his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>Jubilee,</hi> or ſeventh Vial, called his reſt, which is a fulſilling all his Commands, Ye ſhall keep my Sabbath Ordinances, and not break my reſt: In a word, the Prieſts of God muſt be free from all outward inheritance, and in caſe of want, they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully eat and drink with ſuch as be receivers at the Altar of God. <hi>Prieſt I am your Inheritanee,</hi> Deutr. 14.29. declareth of their not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any inheritance: and becauſe of the uncertainty of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, therefore they ſhall eat and drink with the fatherleſſe: this alarm in <hi>Sion</hi> cometh home to our <hi>Miniſters, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Levites.</hi> Under the Law it was to them but a time, but to our Teachers for a ſhorter time: And if the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> failed under the time of the Law, how much more ſhall it do under the Goſpel? By this high <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and his eternal <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and upon the third appearance, your preaching ſhall ceaſe, and that ſhall be, when the two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall ſtand up to plead for Gods heritage, and the peoples Inheritance; and at their appearing your preaching muſt ceaſe, which is the partiality of one mans tongue: for God will have two faithful Witneſſes to plead in your Churches, that ſhall ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Conſciences of the hearers.</p>
            <p>Yet farther, Gods Miniſters ought not to ſtain themſelves with worldly cares, having food and rayment wherewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, which is not ſo low a condition as our Saviours were, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no where to hide his head. Miniſters, what do you fear? if God hath an Houſe, and in it a Common Treaſury, then fear not but the Church ſhall miniſter to your wants; and be not offended though we move you to the Alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; it is not an Altar ſet up in your Churches to bow unto, but it is to the Altar of God, that ſhall alter your Cuſtomes, and prieſtly powers, <hi>Leviticus</hi> 27.30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.29. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12, 13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.9. &amp; 18.1,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42837:12"/>2. the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> ſhall have no Inheritance with Iſrael, therefore ſhall they have no inheritance among their brethren.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if Chriſt Jeſus had given his Diſciples the benefit of Tythes, then might our Miniſters lawfully demand them as their dues; but they nor we cannot find it ſo: it were denyed under the Law, and we have no Goſpel for it; therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ye rob me in tythes and offerings,</hi> Malachy 3.8, 9, 10. Miniſters, are your Ordinances the ſame that Chriſt inſtituted to his Diſciples? otherwiſe they be but humane or mens Ordinances ſet up by your father Biſhops. You ſay we walk above Ordinances; it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed we walk above your ordinances, in that we walk up to the Ordination of Chriſt and his Diſciples, which you deny to the people, which is the true adminiſtration of the everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which we be all ingaged to plead for, even that truth: and no better foundation can any man lay, then that of our Lord and his Diſciples, and ſo far as ye preach forth that doctrine, ſo far we will obey you, and no further. Is your Authority and Calling from the Royal Prieſthood, or from the Levitical Prieſthood? there can but one of them ſtand, which is the new and living way conſecrated to men, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He is our High Prieſt over the Houſe of God; and he hath laid the foundation. So follow him, according to Gods Order and appointment.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:42837:13"/>
            <head>The Miniſterial Duty.</head>
            <p>BRethren beloved in the Lord, I am bold to write unto you, for a more ſtability and amplitude of the <hi>Church;</hi> Hence it is, that God hath oftentimes ſpoken by the mouth of his Prophets, ſaying; <hi>I will put my Law in your hearts, and write it in your inward parts:</hi> So that in thoſe times, and at that day, people ſhall be inherently taught of God, and ſhall be free from mens teaching, and void of preaching. But ſome may ſay, <hi>To what end ſhall this be?</hi> To this objection there be divers anſwers; As for the firſt, <hi>Jeremy</hi> the 32. <hi>I will give them one heart, for the good of them and their children after them;</hi> this promiſe actually is made out to his Elect, in that ſtate of knowing God. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Every one ſhall live under his own Vine; Meaning Chriſt and his ſpirit, with the life of God dwelling in us, which ſhall be our teacher; <hi>For ye ſhall all know me ſaith the Lord.</hi> That is, under the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> which is his third or fourth diſpenſation. Verily, there were a knowing of God before the Law or Goſpel was taught; For it is ſaid about the 7. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that bleſſed <hi>Noah</hi> walked with God; And <hi>Abraham</hi> before the Goſpel, he was taught of God, and lived by faith, and it was accounted to him for righteouſneſs; which paſſed all the outward declarations. Now under the Goſpel here is a knowing of God too, though as yet under a humane power, which may then be taken away. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31. <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. <hi>They ſhall teach no more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42837:13"/>man his neighbour or his brother, ſaying know the Lord; for they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt to the greateſt of them.</hi> And at that time there ſhall be a far higher and clear ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beholding of God, when Freedome hath taken off the curſe, and Juſtice hath deſtroyed all oppreſſion, then preaching may ceaſe, for your children ſhall be as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and your off-ſprings ſhall be proſperous: and ſo it was before, and ſo it ſhall be after this Miniſtry may ceaſe. Our Saviour by his Diſciples ſettled the Church, and laid the foundation, which is called <hi>the living stone,</hi> which were the Goſpel ſetled about 1600 yeares agone, which were a ſufficient foundation; and our preaching hath been little leſſe then 100 yeares or thereupon, which is contrary to the Goſpel which they held forth; for Chriſt and his Apoſtles held forth the outward with the inward, ſaying, <hi>If ye will be my Diſciples, ye muſt leave all to follow me.</hi> Ye muſt not onely follow me in ſpirituall things, but put off your carnal things: this was his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples care to the Church, that not any ſhould want, and in caſe of neceſſity none ſhould know their own; which if we were ſo taught of God, it ſhould do ſo likewiſe, that is, to do the works of the ſecond Table with the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that would truly adorn the Church of God: and truly I much marvel how our preachers have fallen from this doctrine? It is a great ſtarving the creatures of God, that ſome have too much, and ſome deſtroyed by wants, and in this our Miniſtry can ſhew no true calling, in that the livelihood of the Creation is withheld from them which be Gods creatures, and our Miniſters will not lay open the ungodly abuſe of them that carry the world on ſo: for the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe ſhould have an outward calling as well as an inward, and in caſe they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42837:14"/>fail in any of them, they are then but Truth-breakers, and fail in their Meſſage to God, and will not lay open thoſe full Truths; therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ye ſhall be inwardly taught of me, and all know me:</hi> and whoſoever hindereth this work of reſtoration, they be but murtherers of truth and juſtice, whether they be miniſters of men; for behold and ſee what oppreſſion is taken away by your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: There were a two-fold curſe under the old Law, which in part is taken away, the inward and ſpiritual curſe is taken off by the ſufferings and power of Chriſt; now this outward curſe ſtill abideth with us, and ſo ſhall do till the horn of oppreſſion be broke, and for that end God plagued the earth after the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying, it <hi>ſhould bring forth bryers and thornes,</hi> which are wicked men Rulers, as bryers in the hedge of Gods garden; now I can aſſure you that are the Vine-dreſſers, if you do not cut out all theſe bryers and abominable branches out of his hedge; it will ſhew ye are not faithful to him, nor good Stewards in your places: Now this three or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold curſe lying ſo heavy upon man, as firſt a natural curſe, in lying under a ſad and dark diſpenſation, which is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual diſſertion which every one of us lye under, till God comes in to our ſoules: And thirdly, that legall curſe which is the hand-writing of ordinances under a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral declaration of Gods Juſtice. Now theſe three Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes being taken away and cenſured by the Lord Chriſt, yet there is one curſe more for us to take off, which is our oppreſſion in the world as man to man, which eateth out all Chriſtian community, and cauſeth men to lead brutiſh lives in reſpect of that life they ſhould continue in under him, which is our life.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42837:14"/>
            <p>Now this outward curſe being ſo inordinate amongſt us, that I think men and miniſters be all inherently accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they cannot neither will they ſee the evill of an oppreſſing State, which canſeth all to be out of order: Now God hath taken off three curſes from of man, which we could not have done by our ſelves: the fourth is left to man or mens power, that they ſhould thorowly purge the world of all tranſgreſſion, and of every curſed thing, behold all your affaires are left upon the record of your conſciences, and ſo long as ye keep back the full freedom of Gods bounty, and puniſh your brethren by this oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtate, you lye under a far worſe curſe and judgement then they that ſuffer under your yoke and bondage; for they ſuffer but a little outward want and grief, which is nothing to your eternal ſuffering; ye Miniſters preach on, but what oppreſſion is taken away, or as we may ſay, what wound is cured? Now if Truth were reſtored, and Juſtice, we ſhould then be truly <hi>taught of God,</hi> and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing might ceaſe. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32. <hi>verſ.</hi> 40. <hi>I will put my fear in your hearts, that ye ſhall not depart from me:</hi> For it is God alone that keepes us in our Chriſtian way, and ſtayeth us up by his helpful Spirit; for ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will write my Law in your hearts;</hi> ſo that we find Gods Spirit is and ſhall be our onely teacher. It is not your external prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that ſhall beget ſoules, or actually regenerate; <hi>it is God that worketh the will and the deed:</hi> ye may informe or ſtrengthen the weak, or keep your people under an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conformity, but not to beget or ſaved ſoules, for that is Gods ancient work of old called Election; therefore ye Miniſters ye are called but <hi>Labourers in his vineyard,</hi> to keep things in order. But truly we have many Miniſters in this Kingdome that are more fit to be taught, then to be Teachers: yet ſome of them will ſay, I have begotten
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42837:15"/>many ſouls; as if an outward act could do it. But I ſay no, for it is the inward working of God that doth it. If God did not work it, our Miniſters might ſtand long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in their Pulpits, your preaching doth neither hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nor further ſalvation, it is onely Gods purpoſe, and not your preſervation. <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, but God proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; He is the Foundation of our life, and he will teach us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall all know me, from the least to the greatest;</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould ye Divines be ſo high conceited in your ſelves, your way of preaching is not ſo ancient as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles was, neither have ye done ſo much good as they did, in that ſhort time they taught the Goſpel; for they taught their hearers to throw up the poſſeſſions, which was true Goſpel, but I ſee no ſuch matter by your new found Doctrine, and your foundation cannot hold, it is ſomething too young: For the Apoſtles foundation was not onely laid 1600 years agone, which is ancient, but Chriſt Jeſus was their Author and finiſher of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and for that cauſe he ſuffered, which proved it true Goſpel; But what our Miniſters have made on it, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell, but this I am ſure, they have changed thoſe Ordinances of Chriſt, and thoſe which they have ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, will hardly be proved true Goſpel; they carry it on with a power which ſhall fall with <hi>Babylon.</hi> It is not your Miniſtery which ſhall ſtand, for yee divine for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſome of yee will leave your people for gain: But the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>Come buy wine and milk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money.</hi> But many doth now both buy and ſell the word of God; as by Funeral-Sermons, receiving money; Or by a mariage Exhortation: Oh what Task-maſters bee theſe? to ſtand two, three, or four hours in a Pulpit (as ye call it.)</p>
            <p>Alas, it is not your way to ſave ſouls, it is proper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42837:15"/>to God; ye may counſell them, or inform your people, which all you can do. For God ſaith, <hi>I will write my Law in your inward parts;</hi> And what he hath ſo done, you can but preach the Letter to the people; But God miniſtreth the Spiritual guift to the hearer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth grace in the heart: It is Chriſts feet that are beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and bringeth ſalvation; all your external preachings without Gods internal work, is nothing. Yet for all this, I have heard ſome of our Miniſters ſay, <hi>they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got ſouls:</hi> which is but a vain pamphlet.</p>
            <p>Again, I can give relation of a godly man, that ſaid ſuch a Miniſter was his adapted father, ſo that men or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may err in the ſectet works of Gods election, reſting upon vain dictates and ſelf ends, which is a meritorious work to do; for he that aſcribeth any power to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he taketh away and diminiſheth the power of Chriſt, and without the ſpirit of God, what can ye do? A Lay man having Gods ſpirit, may do as much as you can do, ſetting your trade aſide, which is La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and Logick, learned at Oxford and Cambridg, which edifieth not the ſoul; you be one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which ſheweth your Temple is not yet built in its own place. Levi perſecuteth which the tongue, and Reuben looketh high, ſo that as yet Judah can have no entrance: Behold all your Churches muſt come to a Synod, which is a grand conſent to make up one model or holy lump, called one unto the Lord, for God will not behold all your mental knowings, Ye muſt all know me; He will have but one way, and one Church, which is the ancient foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; and I know none other.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42837:16"/>
            <p>Therefore come and acknowledge <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-builder, <hi>Ye ſhall all know me;</hi> That is, the major or vulgar ſort of people ſhall ſo know God, that they ſhall put down your power, I mean your Miniſterial prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: For <hi>God</hi> his will and power are both one, and he laid them both upon that foundation, which we bee all called to build upon. I am aſhamed of your ignorance, both miniſters and hearers, if otherwiſe ye know and do not reform and comeout form the people; your bloud be upon your own heads: For I cannot but ſpeak the things I have heard and ſeen, deſiring the Lord of his goodneſs to open your eys, that ye may ſee this main work. Ye ſhall all know me, that is, to be King, prieſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: As he is King, to govern; and as hee is both prieſt and prophet, ſo to be all our teachers. And out Lord ſaith, <hi>No man can come unto me, except it be given him of the Father:</hi> So it is not your teachings that ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſouls, for then and at that time, there ſhall bee one Prieſt one people, which is a living under their own Vine Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55. <hi>He hath given him to be a Leader to them, a witneſs and a Commander to the pesple;</hi> ſo that it is Chriſt Jeſus alone that begetteth ſouls. And at that time he ſhall be the onely teacher, when you Prieſts ſhall move out of their holes. <hi>Micha</hi> 3. and ſhall not divine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more; when Viſion ſhall ceaſe, and we ſhall come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him which is the patifical Viſion, which is our beauty in perfection. <hi>When all mens teachings ſhall fail, then our true Vine ſhall be the Teacher, when we ſhall dwell under our own fig-tree; ye ſhall no more ſay, know the Lord, for ye ſhall all know me.</hi> And to winde up this diſcourſe, our Lord ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.45. <hi>It is written in the Prophets, that they ſhall all be taught of God;</hi> So that all of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhall walk in that Light, above mens teachings.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DENUS <hi>to the reſtored Church, in the Iſle of</hi> Pathmos.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42837:16"/>
            <head>The perſonal Reign of the Saints.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REvel.</hi> 5.9. <hi>And they ſang a new Song, ſaying; Thou art worthy to open the ſeals, for thou waſt ſhame, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy bloud, out of every kinred, people, tongue and nation, and haſt made us Kings and Prieſts to God, and we ſhall reign on the earth.</hi> This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, beareth us up by a living hope, and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, we look for new heavens, and a new earth, where Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall dwell; Theſe words have an inference to a new ſtate of Juſtice, when none ſhall reign but his kingdom of Saints, which muſt execute juſtice under him by a perſonal power, in ſo high an enjoyment of God, that they well be called a new heaven on earth, or an heavenly people that ſhall reign on earth, ſo that the world ſeeing their high and ſweet enjoyment, may imitate them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a new earth, and ſo comply and rejoyce together: As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rejoyce ye Gentile with his people;</hi> ſo that the natural branch may rejoyce with the ſpiritual kingdom and government, and grift in with them to ſing to God, ſaying; <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord.</hi> This perſonal reign of the Saints ſhall be a viſible State that the ends of the earth ſhall have, when the oppreſſours ſhall no more paſs through their kingdom or City; <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.8. when they ſhall have all given into their hands: As you may finde by <hi>Daniel</hi> the 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. That the dominion and greatneſs of the kingdom, ſhall be given to the people of the Saints. <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. Saying, <hi>Ye ſhall be Kings and Prieſts to God, and ſhall reign with him.</hi> Which is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by ſome, that Chriſt ſhall reign with his people again in a perſonal or viſible eſtate, which he hath done already upon his participation; but now we look only to his ſubſtantiality, and to bring all into the God-head; which is one ſubſtance, almighty, and king of Saints, without perſon or perſons; which is an undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſubſtance, moſt high, whoſe kingdom is an everlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him, which is God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42837:17"/>without end, or dividing into parts any more; For the Lord ſhall raign in Sion, before his ancient glory, and the earth ſhall be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced, when the Saints ſhall grown in that new heaven, <hi>and</hi> ſhall raign as Kings over the world, in that high calling, and Royal Prieſthood: the Lord will do great things, at that time the Saints ſhall bear the Image of the heavenly, by a ſure walking with God: for he hath made us Kings and Prieſts to him, and we ſhall raign on the earth, when he hath put all rule and Authority un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet; he ſhall give up the kingdom to his father, and ſhall raign, and ſhall put all powers under him. I do not mean that Chriſt ſhall raign perſonally any more, but as in power in all places, both in Heaven, and Earth: as Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt joyned all in one power, and the Saints ſhall govern as Deputies under him: for <hi>David</hi> ſhall never want a man, nor the people of God a Prieſt, to offer ſacrifices continually, which is him above: for no fleſh ſhall behold any more, but by his power, and not by his bodily ſhape: the ſoul may behold him when it is out of the body, and for any further beholding of him I know none: for his perſonall raign hath been already, and he hath appeared to his Diſciples, ſaying, go forth and declare as by a perſonall command, So it appeared.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Haſilwood,</hi> dwelling in the Pariſh of <hi>Windſor,</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks.</hi> 1651.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42837:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
